Hello and welcome back to another
video with ItsDrDan, and today I'm
going to be explaining to you what
is chirality, especially looking
at enantiomers and diastereomers.
And we're going to look at a bunch
of different examples as well to
try to explain what this concept is.
Now what this all has to do with
is different carbons, just like
the one here, that have four
completely unique groups around them.
So whenever there are four different
groups, what can happen is that when
it looks at its reflection, they
are completely different, right?
You are not able to superimpose them.
Now what does that mean if
I can't superimpose them?
Well, let's say if I have my right
hand and I want to wave it at you.
Now you might see like, Oh, wait a minute.
That's not your right hand.
That's your left hand.
Well, it's all about reflections, right?
Well, let's try to look at this in terms
of a camera to try to understand that.
Let's use two of me to help explain this.
So if I wave, let's say if I want to
wave my right hand, just like so, and
you could see, Hey, wait a minute,
they're both waving opposite hands.
Well, this is the whole entire
idea as waving at your reflection.
So if I use my right hand and I wave it
at my other reflection, notice how it's
waving its left hand side, and they're
both waving completely different hands.
Well, if I take my hands as well,
and I try to look at them, and I
try to look at both your hands,
well, you can't overlap them.
Meaning that if I put them on top
of each other, notice how my thumbs
are in opposite positions, right?
So you cannot overlap them.
So they might be able to be
reflections of one another, right?
So if I kind of show that my thumbs
are both reflecting, I can try to
show how they're reflections this way.
But I can't overlap them.
It's the same idea as looking
at my reflection, right?
Both sides, we could be
waving at one another.
We're both waving opposite hands.
It's the same idea.
Look at yourself in the mirror,
try to wave to yourself and you'll
notice it's the opposite side.
So what does this have
to do with chemistry?
Well, if you have, let's say an
enantiomer or mirror images of each
other, they're each going to have
their own completely unique properties
behind each of these molecules.
Especially if you look at things like in
biochemistry, where if you have proteins
and enzymes and they have to bond to each
other in specific ways to allow a reaction
to happen, well if it's not in the right
orientation, it's not going to bond.
In fact, in some pharmaceutical
chemicals, right, one might be a drug
that might cure something in your
body, the other one might be a harmful
toxin, which is something that's
commonly found in the world around us.
So let's try to take a look at this
concept, we're going to be moving through
this and trying to understand this, so
let's look at some different examples for
me to try to explain chirality to you.
Let's take a look.
In
order for something to be chiral,
we have to first try to understand
not only just reflections but this
concept of four unique groups.
So what I have here is I have a circle
drawn, and I have four different
colors, and in the middle of these
colors, we have an intersection.
That intersection is your carbon, right?
So the carbon meets every
single different group.
So if I have, let's say my mirror,
which I have drawn in blue, what
exactly would that reflection be, right?
We have completely different mirrors.
It's the same thing as looking
at the reflection of myself
from earlier in this video.
Now whenever we have two chiral carbons,
or sorry, two different chiral molecules.
And we have their mirror images,
these are referred to as enantiomers,
meaning that they are reflection.
Notice how the light, the teals line
up, the blues line up, yellows line
up, and reds go inside and outside.
The other thing that's pretty cool
about it is that, okay, well, if
I take this thing, I can try to
overlap it as well, and I can see,
do those different colors line up?
Now, one thing that we can
always try to do is, well, can
I make it where they line up?
And we can attempt to rotate this thing,
right, just like so, and I can try
to see, like, well, does it line up?
And it doesn't.
There's no way.
We just start making different colors.
We can't make it line up, which
is something that's really, really
difficult when we're looking
at these types of molecules.
Whenever they are enantiomers, that means
that they are reflections of one another,
however, they are not superimposable,
meaning that you can not overlap them.
So, not superimposable,
meaning no overlap.
Now, when depending on the
molecules you have drawn, you
could have chiral molecules that
are identical to one another.
that maybe are, let's say,
in a different arrangement.
So let's say if I cut out this one on the
right and I re copy and paste the one on
the left, Well, if I have this structure,
sometimes the molecule just might be
in a slightly different orientation.
So if you try overlapping it,
it might look like they are two
completely different things.
You might say they're enantiomers.
However, you need to make sure
you are rotating and looking at
molecules because sometimes They
can just be identical molecules.
Notice how they're both chiral, but
in this case they are both the same.
So we're going to look at
examples of that in a little bit.
Let's take a look at what
achiral means, or not chiral.
Achiral molecules.
What this means is not chiral,
meaning that we're going to ignore
certain groups around a carbon.
Now what are we ignoring?
Well, we want to ignore things
with three or less unique groups.
So we need to have four things.
So it has to be tetrahedral
and all four have to be unique.
So we want to ignore
things like CH3, right?
Because there are three hydrogens.
CH2, that's two hydrogens.
Double bonds, double methyls,
symmetry, things like that.
Now why is that?
Well, both of these you can see I have
two teal sections of this molecule.
Meaning, that we have three unique groups.
Well, can't you say, well they
look completely different?
They should be chiral.
However, one thing that you can do
is, if I turn this Notice how they
are completely the same, and if I try
to overlap them, well, their white
and yellow also overlaps as well.
So we have not only achiral molecules,
but they're the same exact thing.
You're able to overlap achiral as well.
It doesn't have that optical property.
Let's take a look at some
different examples and see how
we can apply this to molecules.
Looking at molecules is a lot easier
when you are using models, and that's
something that's a very harsh reality for
any student that is beginning at organic
chemistry, or in chemistry in general.
One of the things that we try to teach
our students is that you need to be
able to visualize these molecules and
try to see what they really look like.
We might write them on a sheet
of paper, but all these different
molecules, they are three dimensional.
They are things that rotate
and move and change, right?
So if we are ever to look at models, we
can always see that these things have
a three dimensional perspective, and
we need to be able to understand that.
And it's really difficult to do,
especially at first, but it's
something that comes with practice
and the more you look at it.
Now, when it comes to a lot of these
structures, we have to remember our
three dimensional VSEPR geometries.
So let's say if you didn't, don't
remember for this video, right?
One way that I'm representing
these, I have lines here.
These are always
referring to in the plane.
Meaning, what does that refer to?
Well, if you think of your computer
screen or your monitor that you're
looking at right now and it's flat, well,
that means that these two bonds that
are on the left and on the top, they
are in line with your monitor, right?
Now the wedge, this means
that it's coming towards you.
So I like to think it's
boldly coming towards you.
So usually this is kind of darkened
and shown as a big bold line.
So that means it's boldly coming out
of the screen right at you, right
now, whenever it comes to a dash.
The, the way you can think of
this as, Oh, I'm dashing away
or it's a fade away, right?
You see that it is fading
into the background.
So like, this is like, it's going
behind you or going like behind
your monitor realistically when
you are looking at this video.
Now if we take this molecule and
the whole idea here is that we want
to be able to build these, right?
You need to actually try to
understand that if we are to
put these things together.
We need to build it just like we see it
now The big thing is I always tell my
students is you want to first start with
just your carbon atom by itself, right?
So I have a black ball here.
Carbon is the black one now
if we have hydrogen, right?
Hydrogen is going in line with the
plane This is going to be flat like
this pointing up now The other part is
that we have a hydrogen as you can see
on the right right here is going to be
pointing out So we're also going to put
that flat in line with each other You
Now, we have a chlorine that's boldly
coming out towards you, so we're going
to put that chlorine right there coming
right at the camera, and then we will
put the bromine all the way in the back.
Now, being able to build models is
something that's a very crucial skill.
So let's say if I want to do the
exact same thing, and let's say
if I make a mirror image of that,
well, what exactly does that mean?
And is this something that's chiral?
or achiral.
Now, when we are looking at both
these, right, we can try to analyze
these different models and we can
try to compare them to each other.
Can we make them as mirror images, right?
So, the whole idea is that let's say if
I have them both facing each other and
we can see that, all right, we have the
two red, the two red ones facing each
other, the white ones are in line with
each other, we can see that these are
complete mirror images of one another.
As a result, and when they are
mirrors, well, are they enantiomers?
Well, that comes down to identifying, do
we have four completely different groups?
And one thing you can see is that
there are two hydrogens here.
So what does that exactly mean?
Well, we don't have four.
So this is an achiral molecule.
They can still be mirrors of one another.
However, they need to, they need to
be chiral in order to be enantiomers.
Going back to that, well, that just
means that we have two chiral, so we
have achiral molecules, sorry, and they
are mirrors, however, they are achiral.
Let's take a look at the next example.
Okay, our first example, are the
following molecules enantiomers
or are they the same molecule?
Now, in order for them to be enantiomers,
Or the same, what does that exactly mean?
Well, same just tells
you they're identical.
Not that they are achiral or
chiral, just that they're identical.
So in order to first, we need
to determine are they chiral?
Well, if I go through these, I
can try to always highlight that I
have four completely unique groups.
So we can see we have a
chlorine, a bromine, an OH.
So we have four different things
on each of these molecules.
So what that tells you is that we
have two sets of chiral molecules.
Now how can you tell if they're
mirrors, especially when
they're not drawn that way?
Well, the first thing, the easiest
way to do it is by using model kits
and to build them, put them in your
perspective so that way you can see,
do you have the same exact molecule?
So that's what I did.
So what I usually always try to do
is I try to see, can I reflect them?
And then what I'll do is I'll see if I
can overlap or superimpose them to see,
hey, do I have the exact same structure?
So here I have both of
these different molecules.
So I have the one that we had
on the left hand side, right?
I have the OH kind of
pointing, uh, towards you guys.
And then I have, uh, the chlorine and the
hydrogen, they are in the plane, right?
So I see the OH out front, and then the
chlorine and the hydrogen in the plane.
Now, the other thing that we're
going to be showing here is that if
I look at these, I have my other one
as well, and I built this one too.
Now the thing about it is it's
not in the same perspective.
So what you want to do is you
want to line up, let's say if we
make both the OHs face each other.
We have the hydrogens face each
other, and then I also have both
of the chlorines in the same spot.
And really what you can see is
that, hey, both of these, all these
different species are on the same side.
And it's like you have the little
OHs waving at each other, like the
reflection that I showed earlier, right?
So both of these are
mirrors of each other.
So notice how everything is a mirror.
So we can see that they
all line up as well.
So these are referring to that they
are enantiomers of one another, right?
So these are mirrors.
So now when it comes to a mirror,
one thing that you want to try to
do for yourself is attempt to rotate
these in your head to see like, okay,
how does this entire thing change?
And one thing that you usually
can see with enantiomers is two
of the groups are usually flipped
when you have the enantiomer.
So you notice the hydrogen and the
chlorine, they're flipped on one
another on this one chiral center.
So most likely this has a chance
that it's going to be a reflection
when it's just one chiral carbon.
So this is the idea.
Now let's try to take a
look at a different one.
Let's say if I propose the same
question with a different molecule.
Let's take a look.
Now with this type of problem,
there are two ways to do this one
that makes it a little easier.
Thank you.
What we're trying to do is see are
all the groups in the same general
position now or are they enantiomers?
So if we want to look notice how
the CH3s are in the same spot So
one thing that this kind of tells
you is that when it comes to a CH3
So that's what I'm holding now.
The other portion rotates
like a pinwheel, right?
These bonds they can rotate so if
it's a single bond They can rotate.
So one thing that we can actually
see with this molecule is let's say
if I rotate each of these positions
around like it's a pinwheel.
And what does that exactly
do to the structure?
Well if I do that, well how
is that going to change?
Well I will have a CH on top.
I'll have my bromine all of a sudden
on the bottom, and then I'll have my
chlorine will move to the right hand side
of the molecule, just like so, and the
CH3 is the part that we were holding.
So, what do you see about
these two molecules now?
They are identical to one another.
So these are the same
molecule or identical.
So when you are going through these,
try to see, can you hold one part
to be the same and then rotate the
other three like it's a pinwheel.
Now how does this look up close?
Well, if I take this exact same model,
and I hold it up to, let's say, another,
um, another form that is identical to it.
So one thing we can kind of see if
we hold up those chiral carbons.
is that the, the reds will line
up, but notice how the blue and
white does not quite line up.
So what we can attempt to do is line up
all the pieces, just like so, and you
can see the blue parts are generally in
the same spot, and the white parts are
in the same spot, the red parts are in
the same, that they overlap with one
another, making these the same molecule.
Let's take a look at diastereomers
and how we can determine
these types of structures.
Diastereomers are something that's
very, very different and can be
a big struggle for introductory
organic and biochemistry students.
In order for a diastereomer to
be possible, you have to have
at least two chiral carbons.
They cannot be mirrors of each
other and they cannot overlap,
meaning they are not superimposable.
These are things that are commonly seen in
biochemistry, especially revolving around
Fischer projections, commonly found in
the carbohydrate family in biochemistry.
So, if I have the following structure
here, so I have a biochemical species.
Now what we're going to do is
we're going to first, we're going
to draw the mirror image of this.
So what I do is I have these
kind of pre prepared down here.
So let's say if I take that mirror
image and I bring it up top, now one
thing we can see is that we have two
complete reflections of one another.
These are referred to as enantiomers,
just like we did earlier.
Notice how the OHs line up.
So this is what the trick is to try to
figure out, is there a diastereomer?
Remember, they cannot be enantiomers.
So how can you tell?
Well, what I'm going to do is I'm
going to highlight the OH groups.
So you can see that those
things are highlighted, right?
And let's see if I can
pick a better color.
So OHs are, are highlighted.
Notice how we have three OH's on
each side, it's a pattern, right?
OH, OH, OH.
Let's take a look at, let, if I
put a, another, molecule up here.
And we'll put another line down.
So in order to have, let's say a
diastereomer, let's do the same thing.
Or now I'm going to
highlight the OHs again.
So if we can look, notice how the
pattern does not match up, right?
On the right hand side,
we have -OH, -H, -OH.
So what that tells you is, hey,
this is not that three OH combo.
So compare your sides.
Look at a side now where what is
a diastereomer in reference to
well It's a it's a diastereomer
to both of the other structures.
So let's say if I label these structure 1
structure 2 structure 3 So the way to do
this is that 1 and 2 are enantiomers of
one another now What are diastereomers?
Well 1 and 3 are diastereomers Right.
And one, or sorry, and two
and three are diastereomers.
So what that means is that all of
the structures are diastereomers
in reference to number three.
But they have different kind of
meanings or connotations behind
what kind of diastereomer.
And this has to do with carbon numbering.
So, for example, if I number this
like carbons so starting at the most
oxidized on top, which, what changes?
Well, if I compare number 3 and
number 1, notice how carbon 3 changes.
So what this is referring to
is a C3 epimer for 1 and 3,
meaning that carbon 3 flipped.
So that tells you that it's an
epimer of the other structure.
Now in terms of 2 and
3, well, what flipped?
Well, 2 and 4 flipped.
So it's kind of like a
diepimer, there's doubles.
But generally we only refer to it for
1 carbon when talking about an epimer.
So when it comes to a lot of the
carbohydrates that are naturally in
your body, like glucose and all the
other, like lactose and a lot of
these other carbohydrates, especially
the six carbon species, we ingest
many of these different sugars.
But a lot of them, they're just
differing by one OH that's being flipped.
Each of these cross sections up here,
these are all chiral carbons, right?
They all have four unique groups,
but one of them is switching, right?
So all these have three chiral carbons
that are here, but you see one switching.
So that's the idea.
The trick is, is look at each of your
sides, and if you see one flipped,
you have a diastereomer on your hands.
Now, I hope that this video
helped in terms of chirality.
Keep in mind you're looking
for four unique groups.
Please watch my follow up video on
how to find chiral carbons so that
way it can better help you understand
chirality and to better master this.
This has been Dr.
Dan here and please hit that like and
subscribe button and come back for future
videos on introductory organic to help
you pass your organic chemistry course.
I hope to see you all in the future and
I hope you all have a wonderful day.
Bye now.